Guide to the William Trelease papers, [ca. 1862-1945].
Trelease, William papers, [ca. 1862-1945].
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Trelease papers, [ca. 1862-1945].
2560
William Trelease, 1857-1945.
3 linear ft.
Correspondence, clippings, photographs, deeds, drawings, and other material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
General incoming personal and professional correspondence, c. 1879-c. 1845; correspondence, clippings, and other items concerning his work in the Missouri Botanical Gardens, his monographs, the naming of Mount Trelease, Colorado, activities of the Society of American Bacteriologists, and other subjects; and photographs and miscellaneous printed matter. Also Trelease's correspondence, deeds, and drawings concerning family cemetery plots in Urbana, Illinois, and St. Louis Missouri.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Botany at Wisconsin, Washington, and Illinois Universities, 1883-1912; and director, Missouri Botanical Gardens, 1889-1912.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
General incoming personal and professional correspondence, c. 1879-c. 1845; correspondence, clippings, and other items concerning his work in the Missouri Botanical Gardens, his monographs, the naming of Mount Trelease, Colorado, activities of the Society of American Bacteriologists, and other subjects; and photographs and miscellaneous printed matter. Also Trelease's correspondence, deeds, and drawings concerning family cemetery plots in Urbana, Illinois, and St. Louis Missouri.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Trelease, William, 1857-1945.; Missouri Botanical Gardens.; Society of American Bacteriologists.; University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.; University of Washington.
Subjects:
Botanical gardens--Missouri--St. Louis.; Botany--Study and teaching.; Cemeteries--Illinois--Urbana.; Cemeteries--Missouri--St. Louis.; Botanists--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Professional correspondence from Anna Botsford (1854-1930) and John Henry Comstock (1849-1931)., [1879-1884]-1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Professional correspondence from William R. Dudley (1849- ), Mar.-Nov. 1880 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Professional correspondence, mostly from J.B. Ellis, 1882-1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Professional correspondence and personal correspondence from George J. Engelmann, M.D., 1886-1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence from W.G. Farlow, 1880-1886 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
- Correspondence from W.G. Farlow, 1887-1894 (Box 1, Folder 5b)
- Correspondence from W.G. Farlow, 1895-1903 (Box 1, Folder 5c)
- Professional correspondence from Simon Henry Gage (1851-1944), [1880-1888]-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Professional correspondence from W.R. Gerard, 1880-1885 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Personal and professional correspondence from George Lincoln Goodale (1839-1923), 1881-1888 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Professional correspondence from Edward Lee Greene (1832- ), 1887-1893 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Professional correspondence from J.H. Mellichamp, 1888-1898 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Professional correspondence from A.S. Packard, Jr., of the Department of the Interior, Entomological Committee, 1879-1880 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Professional correspondence from C.C. Parry, 1888-1889, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Professional correspondence from Charles H. Peck, 1880-1893 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Professional correspondence from Charles Mohr, 1883-1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Professional correspondence from J. Reverchen, 1892-1902 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Professional correspondence, mostly from Joseph Nelson Rose (1862- ), of the Department of Botany at the Smithsonian, 1885, 1892-1898 (Box 3, Folder 1a)
- Professional correspondence, mostly from Joseph Nelson Rose (1862- ), of the Department of Botany at the Smithsonian, 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 1b)
- Professional correspondence from C.V. Riley, 1883-1894 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Professional correspondence from Charles Sprague Sargent (1841- ), 1883-1896 (Box 3, Folder 3a)
- Professional correspondence from Charles Sprague Sargent (1841- ), 1897-1902 (Box 3, Folder 3b)
- 30 typewritten pp., "Gardens and Botanical Gardens" (Box 3, Folder 3b)
- Correspondence (p.c.) between Trelease, Henry Shaw and W.G. Elliot re: Trelease's employment at Missouri Botanical Garden, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- A book of letters, mostly regarding Trelease's retirement from his post at the Missouri Botanical Garden. Many of the letters are from well-known men, such as Roscoe Pound, John Muir, Simon and Susanna Phelps Gage, Liberty Hyde Bailey, David Starr Jordan, and the Comstocks.
  - 1904-1912 (Box 4, Folder 2a)
  - 1912 (Box 4, Folder 2b)
  - 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 2c)
- Missouri Botanical Garden, clippings re: annual reports, 1892-1912 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and other items pertaining to Trelease's "Agave in the West Indies", 1912-1917, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Items pertaining to Mount Trelease, 1932-1933, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photographs of the Boyce Thomson Southwestern Arboretum, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Letters and other items pertaining to Trelease's monograph of "American Oaks", 1925-1935 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, articles, and receipts, 1860-1918 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous correspondence
  - 1925-1927 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1928 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1929 (Box 5, Folder 4a-b)
  - 1930 (Box 6, Folder 1a-b)
  - 1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1933 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1940 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1941, [1942, 1944] (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Letters of condolence, newspaper clippings, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous photographs (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Pamphlets (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Paperbound book, Memoirs of the National Academy of Science, vol. XX (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1924 ). The whole of this volume compromises "The American Oaks," by William Trelease. (Box 7)
- Additional papers, 1914-[1940-1945] (Box 8)
  These additional papers consist mainly of letters from relatives, friends, colleagues, and ex-students on his 80th (1937) and 83rd (1940) birthdays, and letters of condolence (1945) to his widow and children; also included are Trelease's correspondence, deeds, and drawings concerning family cemetery plots in Urban, Illinois and St. Louis, Missouri; William Trelease, Personal Reminiscences by J. Christian Bay (12 pp. pamphlet, 1945); photographs of Trelease; and related printed matter and newspaper clippings. Ca. 150 pcs.
  Correspondents of William Trelease:
  John W. Spargo - cousin - professor at Northwestern University
  Jonibel Blair - granddaughter
  Hillebrand - English professor - Harvard A.B. and Ph.D.
  Albert L. Lybyer - professor of history at Illinois
  Abram Leon Sacher - president of Brandeis University now
  Cecelia Tonton - daughter of H.B. Ward
  Kaltienn M. Noyes - widow of W.A. Noyes (chemist)
  Leighton - Ill. State Geological Survey
  Frank W. Scott - with D.C. Heat, formerly professor at Illinois
  Eunice Daniels - widow of Pres. Daniels